>> SPEAKER: All right, this is CS50.
This is the end of week three, and if
you haven't taken advantage already,
know that there will be lunch
this Friday as usual, where
you can enjoy good conversation
and food at Fire and Ice
with some of CS50's
staff and classmates.
Head to this URL here.
>> Now you may recall, or you
may soon be acquainted with,
these things here, which
are given out at the end
of the semester for many classes.
So-called exam blue books, in which
you write your answers to exams.
Now I have here 26 such
blue books, on each of them
is written a name, A through Z. And
indeed the names are that simple, A
through Z. And one of
the goals at hand today
is going to be to continue what
we started on Monday, which is not
so much looking at code, but really
looking at ideas and problem solving.
One of the goals and
promises of this course
is to teach you to think more
carefully, more methodically,
and to solve problems more efficiently.
And indeed, we can do that really
without even touching a line of code.
So I have a couple of elephants
up here today, orange and blue,
if we could get one volunteer,
maybe from farther back than usual.
How about right there, come on down.
The goal of which is going to be to
help plus administer this exam here.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Mary Beth.
SPEAKER: Mary Beth, come on up.
Let me get the microphone here for you.
Nice to meet you.
>> AUDIENCE: Nice to meet you.
SPEAKER: All right, so I have
here blue books A through Z,
and I'm going to pretend that
I have one of the students,
and they're coming in somewhat randomly
at the end of a three hour exam block,
so they're ending up in some
semi-random order like this.
Now your job in just a moment is going
to be-- this is actually how they get
turned in at the end of
the class, most likely.
Your job now is going to be, quite
simply, to sort these blue books for us
from A through Z.
>> AUDIENCE: Oh, this is
going to take forever.
>> SPEAKER: And we will watch
as you do this, no pressure.
AUDIENCE: No, no pressure or anything.
>> SPEAKER: And for fun,
let's put up a timer.
>> AUDIENCE: So much fun, so much fun.
>> SPEAKER: I can hold the mic for you.
All right, we've just doubled our speed.
So in the meantime, let me pose what's
going to be the question for Mary Beth
is what is she doing, how is
she going about solving this?
And in fact, you might not have
ever thought about something
so simple as when you pick
up 26 books like this,
which do have a natural
ordering to them.
What is the process
that you actually use?
Is it fairly random just
picking the first one you see
and putting it in its place?
Do you first move your hands around
looking for A then looking for B?
Do you take a look at a
pair of them side by side
and just say, wait a minute, this
isn't right, and then swap the order?
We saw already on Monday
that there's a number of ways
in which we can do this, and
indeed as we near the end here,
I would take note perhaps
of what Mary Beth is doing.
We have a few piles it seems, a
bigger one, three smaller ones.
>> AUDIENCE: I'm ordering them
when I find two letters
that I know are together in a sequence,
I put them together so that I don't
have to worry about keeping
track of a whole row of books.
It's just, oh, A is first,
I've got this stack here.
SPEAKER: So, almost like
a puzzle pieces that
have the right shape to
match up with each other.
AUDIENCE: Pretty much, yeah.
SPEAKER: OK, excellent.
And now each of these
piles is presumably sorted?
>> AUDIENCE: Yeah.
>> SPEAKER: All right, A through Z. All
right, congratulations, you did it.
You have your choice.
Blue?
All right, thank you for that.
So Mary Beth did propose
what her approach was,
but what is another approach how you
might go about sorting these things?
What would you have done?
The record to beat would have been
one minute and 50 or so seconds,
plus the ones I forgot to count.
What would you have done?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Take the stack.
Start from the beginning.
Check your papers.
And if the top one is higher
than, maybe, they are,
the bottom one is
higher, then switch them.
>> SPEAKER: OK, so starting
at the top and the bottom,
and then working your way
inward like that, swapping them?
OK, so a little similar
in spirit to bubble sort,
but choosing the extremes
not the adjacent pairs.
But the short of it is that there's
surely a bunch of different ways
we could do this, and
frankly, I think you kind of
adopted a couple approaches, right?
You made sort of four sorted piles, and
then effectively merged them together.
And that's, daresay, another
technique altogether.
You didn't treat it as one big pile,
you divided the problem into four quads,
if you will, and then somehow
merged them in the end.
>> So let's consider, ultimately,
how else we might do this.
We formalized the notion
of bubble sort last time,
and bubble sort recall was an
algorithm that we visualized
with eight of your classmates up here,
seemingly randomly sorted at first.
And we then decided pairwise, if
two elements are out of order,
simply swap them.
So four and two are
obviously out of order,
so those two classmates
switched positions.
And then we repeated with four and six,
then six and eight, on each iteration,
moving to the right.
>> So given eight people, how many pairwise
comparisons did I do while walking from
left to right in one such iteration?
How many comparisons?
Seven, right?
Because if there's eight
people but you have the pair
them and you keep moving
one hop to the right,
you're not going to have eight
comparisons because you can't compare
an element against itself, or it would
just be pointless, so you have seven.
Or more generally, if
we have n people, we
do n minus 1 comparisons
with bubble sort.
>> So let's consider now how good or
bad bubble sort actually was, and try
to give ourselves vocabulary with
which to critique algorithms like this,
and soon our own.
So the first pass through
bubble sort, the first time
I walked from left to right across the
stage, took me n minus 1 comparisons.
And that's going to be my
unit of measure, right?
I was kind of talking and strolling,
somewhat fast, somewhat slow,
so counting my number of seconds
isn't particularly telling,
but counting the number of
operations that I did on Monday,
comparing two people, that feels
like a nice unit of measure.
>> So n minus 1 steps the first time,
but then what happened after that?
What's the one upside of one pass
through an otherwise unsorted list?
What can you tell me about the element
who was all the way over there?
Yeah?
That was the biggest element, right?
Number eight, even though she
started here, every time I
compared her against
a neighbor, she kept
bubbling up to the right
hand side of the list.
And indeed, that's where
the algorithm gets its name.
>> Now by that logic, how many comparisons
need I make on the second time
I make that pass from left to right?
n minus 2, right?
It would just be wasting my time if I
keep comparing eight against someone
else because we already know
she was in the right place.
So that's a bit of an
optimization, so the next pass
is going to be plus n minus two steps,
where n is the number of people.
Now you can kind of extrapolate, even
if you're not a computer scientist,
how this ends.
At the end of this algorithm, presumably
you've got just one comparison left.
You have to kind of fix the
beginning of the list in case two
and one are out of order
and should be one and two,
so this bottoms out at
plus 1 final comparison.
>> Now the dot, dot, dot kind of waves it's
hands at some of the juicier details,
but let's just go ahead and simplify.
If you recall from high
school, frankly, a lot of you
had math books that had
a little cheat sheet
on the front cover or the
back cover that showed you
what series summations like
this ultimately added up to.
In the general case, if you have a
variable like n, and indeed this one,
if you looked at your
old school math book,
you would see that this actually
adds up to this sum here,
n times n minus 1 all divided by 2.
So for now let me just stipulate
this is true, so on a leap of faith,
that's what this sums
up to, and we could
prove that in a more general case.
But now let's expand this out.
So let's multiply this out, so that's
n squared, minus n, all divided by 2.
That's really n squared,
divided by 2, minus n over 2,
so that's all nice and interesting.
But what happens if we
now plug-in a value?
Suppose I didn't have eight
people, but say a million.
And a million just because
it's a pretty big number,
let's plug that in and see what happens.
So if I plug a million into that formula
I'm going to get a million squared,
divided by 2, minus a
million, divided by 2.
Now what's that going to equal?
So 500 billion, minus 500,000.
And if I actually do
that math out, that means
that sorting a million
people with the bubble sort
might take me 499,999,500,000
steps or comparisons in the end,
we're just extrapolating.
>> That feels pretty slow, but frankly
measuring one particular input
like this, isn't all that telling.
But indeed it does suggest that as n
gets larger and larger, this algorithm
kind of feels worse and
worse, or you really
start to feel the pain of that
exponentiation, that n squared,
which adds up pretty fast.
And this detail isn't
lost on people, in fact
some years ago a certain senator who was
campaigning, sat down for an interview
with Google's Eric
Schmidt, CEO at the time,
and was challenged with a question
much like we're exploring today.
Let's take a look.
>> [VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> -Senator, you're here
at Google, and I like
to think of the presidency
as a job interview.
Now, it's hard to get
a job as president,
and you're going through the rigors now.
It's also hard to get a job at Google.
We have questions, and we
ask our candidates questions,
and this one is from Larry Schwimmer.
What-- you guys think I'm
kidding, it's right here.
What is the most efficient way to
sort a million 32-bit integers?
>> -Well--
>> -I'm sorry, maybe--
>> -No, no, no.
I think the bubble sort
would be the wrong way to go.
>> -Come on, who told him this?
I didn't see computer
science in your background.
>> -We've got our spies in there.
>> -OK, let's ask a different
interview question.
>> [END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
>> SPEAKER: So talking about
specific numbers though,
isn't going to be all that useful.
It is not a life lesson that bubble
sort, given a million inputs,
might take as many as 500 billion steps.
You can't really generalize
too effectively from that
and make good design decisions
when writing programs.
So let's focus though on how
we might simplify this result.
>> So I've highlighted in yellow here
the result of n squared divided by 2,
so a million squared
divided by 2, and then
I've highlighted what
the ultimate answer was
once we subtracted off n divided by 2.
And the claim I'm going to make now is,
who the heck cares if you subtract off
a little old n over 2 when the first
part of this formula is so much bigger?
It dominates the other
term, n squared divided by 2
is so much bigger, clearly, as
n gets large like a million,
that is there really a big difference at
the end of the day between 500 billion
and 499,999,500,000?
Not really.
And so what we're going to
do as computer scientists is
ignore those lower order terms and
take something like this and really
just simplify it to the
term that's going to matter.
The bigger our data sets get, the bigger
our databases get, the more web pages
we have to search, the more
friends you have on Facebook.
>> As n gets larger, we're really
going to care about the largest
term in any such analysis of
our algorithms performance.
And I'm going to say, you know what,
bubble sort is on the order of big O,
on the order of n squared.
It's not exactly n
squared as we've seen,
but who really cares
about those smaller terms,
and frankly, who really
cares if we divide by 2?
That's just a constant factor.
And is 500 billion versus 250
billion really that big of a deal?
I could just wait one year,
let my laptop literally
get twice as fast in hardware,
and that sort of difference
just goes away naturally over time.
>> What we care about is
the expression, the part
of the expression that's going to vary
as our input gets bigger and bigger.
And indeed, in the real world,
that's what's happening increasingly
is the inputs to our problems and
algorithms are getting bigger.
So big O is going to be the notation,
the asymptotic notation, that we just
use as computer scientists to describe
the performance, or the running time,
of an algorithm.
So that we can compare algorithms
on different computers written
by different people, by using
some fundamentally similar metric
like the number of comparisons you're
making, or maybe the number of swaps
you're making.
>> What we're not going to
count is the amount of time
that passes on the clock
on the wall typically.
What we're not going to worry
about is how much memory
you're using today at
least, though that's
another resource we might measure.
We're going to try to base our analyses
on just the basic operations, the ones,
frankly, that you can see most visually.
So with something like big O of n
squared, I claim that O of n squared
is an upper bound on the so-called
running time of bubble sort.
In other words, if you
wanted to claim that there's
this upper limit on how many
steps an algorithm might take,
it's going to be in the big O of n
squared in this case, an upper bound.
>> What if I instead change the
story to be not about bubble sort,
but about this upper bound.
Can you think of an algorithm
that we've looked at already
whose upper bound, maximum
measure of time or operations,
would be said to be bounded
by n, a linear function,
not a quadratic one that's curved?
What's an algorithm that
always takes no more
than like n steps, or
2n steps, or 3n steps?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Finding the
biggest number in a list?
>> SPEAKER: Perfect, finding
the biggest number in a list.
If I'm given a list of
people for instance,
each of who is holding a number,
what is the maximum number
of steps it should take me,
a reasonably smart person,
to find the largest person in that list?
n, right?
Because in the worst case, where
might the biggest value be?
Right, all the way at the end.
So in the worst case
upper bound, I might
have to go all the way
over here and be like,
oh, here's number eight,
or whatever that value is.
Now it would just be stupid
if I kept going, right?
Looking for more and more elements
if the last of them is over there?
So surely, n is an upper bound.
I don't need to take
more steps than that.
>> So what if instead I proposed that
there are algorithms in this world that
have a running time that's
bounded by big O of log n, log n?
Where have we seen this before?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: In the phone book problem?
SPEAKER: Like the phone book problem.
What was the measure of how
much time or how many tears it
took me to find someone like
Mike Smith in the phone book?
We claimed it was log n, and
even if unfamiliar or it it's
a little hazy what a
logarithm or exponent was,
just remember that log n
generally refers to the process,
in this case, of dividing
something in half again, and again,
and again, and again, such that it
gets increasingly small as you do that.
>> So log of n refers, sure,
to the phone book example,
to binary search in theory, when we
had the virtual doors on the board,
or when Sean was
searching for something.
If he had used binary search, log n
would be the upper bound on how much
time that takes.
But those algorithms that ran in
log n assumed what key detail?
That the list was sorted, right?
Your algorithm is wrong if
your input is not sorted,
and yet you're using
something like binary search
because you might jump
right over the element
without realizing it's indeed there.
>> Now what might this mean, big O of one?
This doesn't mean that your algorithm
takes one and only one step,
it just means it takes a
constant number of steps.
Maybe it's 1, maybe it's
10, maybe it's 1,000,
but it's independent of
the size of the problem.
No matter how big n is,
a constant time algorithm
always takes the same number of steps.
So what might be an algorithm
we've talked about or just
intuitively that comes to you that
always runs in so-called constant time?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Add two numbers.
SPEAKER: Add two numbers,
2 plus 2 equals 4, done.
So that might work, what else?
How about more real world, yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Finding the
first thing in a list.
SPEAKER: Finding the first
element in a list, sure.
We've actually been talking
about arrays already,
how do you get at the
first element in an array,
no matter how long the
array is in C code?
You just use like the bracket
zero notation, bam, you're there.
And indeed arrays, as an aside,
support something generally known
as random access, random access
memory, because you can literally
jump to any one place.
We can do this even more simply
we can rewind to week zero
when we did Scratch.
How much time did it take for the
say block in Scratch to execute?
Just constant time, right?
Say something, say
something, it doesn't matter
how big Scratches world is, it's always
going to take the same amount of time
to simply say something.
>> So that's constant time,
but what's the flip side?
If that was upper
bounds, what if we want
to describe the lower bounds
of our algorithms running time?
Almost a best case
potentially, if you will,
though these terms could apply to best
cases, worst cases, average cases more
generally, but let's just focus
on lower bounds more generally.
What's an algorithm that has
a lower bound of n steps,
or 2n steps, or 3n steps?
Some factor of n steps,
that's its lower bound.
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: Bubble sort?
>> SPEAKER: Bubble sort takes
you minimally n steps, why?
Why is that?
Why should that start to come to you
intuitively, even if it doesn't just
yet?
Yeah?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER: Exactly.
In the best possible scenario of
bubble sort, and a lot of algorithms,
if I hand you eight people
who are already sorted,
it would be foolish
for you, the algorithm,
to go back and forth
more than once, right?
Because as soon as you
walk through the list once,
you should realize, oh, I made no
swaps, this list is sorted, exit.
But that's going to take you n steps.
>> And conversely, what's another
way of thinking about it?
Bubble sort is an omega,
so to speak, of n,
because if you look at
fewer than n elements, what
is the fundamental issue there?
You don't know if it's sorted, right.
We humans might glance at eight
people and be like, oh, it's sorted,
that didn't take me n steps, but it did.
Your eyes, even though you kind
of have a big field of vision,
you looked at eight elements,
you looked at eight people,
that's eight steps effectively.
And only if I walk through the whole
list do I realize, yes, sorted.
If I stop halfway thinking, all
right, it's pretty sorted so far,
what are the odds it's not sorted?
That algorithms not going to be correct.
Might be faster, but incorrect.
>> So now we have a way of
describing a lower bounds,
and what about constant time?
What's an algorithm that has a lower
bound on its running time of one?
1 step, 2 steps, 10 steps, but
constant, independent of n,
the size of the input?
Yeah, in back.
>> AUDIENCE: Printf?
SPEAKER: What's that?
AUDIENCE: Printf?
SPEAKER: Printf.
OK, sure.
So it takes a fixed number of steps.
And I should now-- now that
we're talking about C code
and not Scratch, something
like say, with printf,
we should start to get careful.
Because printf does take
input, it's a string,
and strings do technically have length.
So if we now want to pick
on you, if you don't mind,
technically we could argue that printf
does take a variable length input,
and surely it might take more
time to print a string this long,
than this long.
>> So what if we consider just the
sorting and searching examples?
What about Mike Smith in the phone
book, or binary search more generally?
In the best case, what might happen?
I open the phone book and, bam,
there's Mike Smith's number.
I can call him right away.
>> Took one step, maybe two steps,
but a constant number of steps
if I got lucky.
And frankly, we saw on
Monday your classmate
get quite lucky twice in a row.
And that was indeed constant
time in a lower bounds
on the algorithm in question for finding
the number 50 behind those closed
doors.
>> Now, as an aside, if you discover
that both big O, the upper bound,
and omega, the lower bound,
are one in the same, that
is the same formula in
parentheses, you can also
say, just to be fancy,
that something is in theta
of n or theta of some other value.
That just means when big
O and omega are the same.
Now what about selection sort?
Let's use this new vocabulary.
In selection sort, what were we
doing again, and again, and again?
I was going back and forth through
the list, looking for whom?
The smallest number.
>> So how many steps, how
many comparisons did I
have to make in order to figure out who
the smallest element in the list was?
n minus 1, right?
Because if I just start with the one I'm
given and I start comparing him or her,
then him or her, him
or her, him or her, I
can only pair elements
together n minus 1 times.
So selection sort similarly takes
n minus 1 steps the first time.
>> How many steps does it take me to
find the second smallest element?
n minus 2, because I'm being dumb
if I keep looking at the same people
again if I've already selected him
or her and put them in their place.
And the third step, n
minus 3, then n minus 4.
We've seen this pattern
before, and indeed
selection sort similarly
has an upper bound
of n squared if we do up that summation.
What is its lower bound, selection sort?
Minimally, how much time must selection
sort take, as we defined it on Monday?
Propose two options.
Maybe it's n, as before.
Maybe it's n squared, as it
is now as the upper bound.
>> AUDIENCE: n squared.
SPEAKER: n squared.
Why?
>> AUDIENCE: Because you have
to define [INAUDIBLE].
>> SPEAKER: Exactly.
At least as I defined selection sort
it was pretty naive, keep going,
find the smallest element.
Go again, find the smallest element.
There's no sort of
optimization in there that
might let me abort after
just n or so steps.
So indeed, selection
sort, omega of n squared.
>> What about insertion sort, where I took
who I was given, and then I plopped him
or her in the right place?
Then I proceeded to the second person,
plopped him or her in the right place.
Then the next person, plopped
him or her in the right place.
Notice that this is very
linear, so to speak.
I'm a straight line, I'm
not going back and forth,
I've never looking back really, but
what's happening when I insert him
or her into the beginning of
the list as we did on Monday?
What's happening?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
SPEAKER: Yeah, that
was the catch, right?
You might recall from
your classmates, if they
were making any movement with
their feet, that was an operation.
So if there were three people here and
the new person belonged way over there,
on a long stage like this, sure, he
or she could just go to the very end.
But if we're thinking about a
computer and an array of memory,
these people are going
to have to shuffle over
to make room for that person.
And so that n minus 1 shufflings,
n minus 2 shufflings, n
minus 3 shufflings is just kind of
happening behind me, not in front of me
as before, in some sense.
Now as an aside, and as
you might have seen online
if you start poking around about
sorts, there's so many different ones
out there, some of them
better than others.
Indeed, bogosort is one
that's kind of fun to look up.
Bogosort takes a set of
numbers or say a deck of cards,
randomly shuffles them, and
checks if they're sorted.
And if not, does it again.
If not, does it again.
Incredibly stupid.
>> And indeed, if you read
like the Wikipedia article,
its nickname is stupid sort.
It will eventually work,
hopefully, given enough time,
but that amount of time
could take quite some time.
So if I could, let's speed things
up from Mary Beth's example earlier,
by having a few more elements,
but two more processors.
Two people, if you
wouldn't mind joining me.
How about 1 over here, and
let's go-- no one over there?
No one over there?
OK.
You with the black
shirt, yes, come on down.
All right, what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Peter.
>> SPEAKER: What's that?
SPEAKER: Peter, David, nice to meet you.
All right, we have Peter here, if you
want to come onto the table over here.
And what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Elena.
SPEAKER: Elena.
OK, nice to meet you.
Elena meet Peter.
Peter, Elena.
And we'll need Andrew
up here as well, please.
And your challenge is going
to be to sort a deck of cards.
And if unfamiliar, deck
of cards should ultimately
be sorted a little something like
this where we'll do the clubs, then
the spades, then the hearts and
diamonds, from ace as a one,
all the way up to king.
>> The cards I'm going to give you
are going to be 52 in quantity.
We're going to similarly
time you, in just a moment.
We're going to throw Andrew
up on the screen here,
so as to watch as you do this.
And so that all of this
is all the more visible,
these are the cards I got on Amazon.
So they are already randomly
sorted, and we're going to time you.
And we're going to
keep it real this time,
so we're going to try to pressure you
because otherwise this will get tedious
quickly.
If you could proceed to sort 52
elements together via some means, now.
>> And again, as we watch these
guys do what, in the end
is going to produce an obvious
result, think about really
how they're each doing it,
how you might describe it.
Because again, these are
all processes, algorithms
that we take for granted as a human.
But you've probably long had
intuition, long before you even
thought about taking a
computer science class you
might have had the intuition with
which to solve problems like this.
But once you recognize
the patterns and begin
to formalize the steps with which
you're solving these problems,
you'll find that you can solve much
more interesting and much more complex
problems quickly.
So someone from the audience, what is
at least one element of the algorithm
that they're using here?
>> AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER: What's that?
AUDIENCE: By suit.
SPEAKER: By suit.
So first they are clustering
all of the diamonds together
it seems, all of the
hearts together it seems,
and so forth, without respect
for the numbers on the cards.
And now they appear, for instance,
to be sorting them by number.
Very good.
>> All right, so what's going to
be the final step then here?
Once we have four sorted suits, what
do we need to do to the four piles
in order to achieve one
sorted deck, quite simply?
So we need to merge them again.
>> So there's an interesting idea that
again, daresay, is very intuitive even
if you might never have slapped
that kind of label on it.
This fundamental notion of dividing
the problem not in half this time,
but at least into four pieces.
Solving pretty much
fundamentally identical problems
in isolation of each other,
and then merging the results.
And, excellent, done.
All right, a big round
of applause, if we could.
>> [APPLAUSE]
>> SPEAKER: I have no idea what you'll
do with these, but here you go.
Thank you so much.
So let's see, two minutes
and eight seconds,
if you'd like to challenge your friends.
What then is going to
be a take away from this
that we can leverage more generally?
Well, think back to
this array of numbers,
and think back now to some of the
pseudocode we've written in the past,
and this was the pseudocode for
solving the phone book problem.
Whereby in pseudocode I
enumerated a more methodical way
of describing how I did a very intuitive
human algorithm of dividing the phone
book in half, repeat, repeat, repeat,
until I find someone like Mike Smith,
if he is indeed in the phone book.
>> But I kind of used what I'll call
a very iterative approach here,
in particular notice line 8 and line 11.
Those are evidence of an iterative
approach, a looping approach,
because that's exactly
the behavior they induce.
Those lines both say go to
line three, and you can kind of
think of that in your
mind's eye as being a loop.
It's telling you to go back up to step
three and repeat, again, and again,
and again.
>> But what if we leverage a key idea
here that we didn't the last time,
and simplify line 8 and
line 11 and their neighbors
as just this, in yellow.
It's not fundamentally shortening
the pseudocode very much,
but it's fundamentally changing
the nature of my algorithm.
What I'm now saying
in step 7, in step 10,
is to search for Mike
in the exact same way,
but just in the left
half or the right half.
>> So in other words, if
I start from step one,
pick up phone book, open to middle
of phone book, look at names,
if Smith is among
name's, call Mike, else
if Smith is earlier in book, step seven
search for Mike in left half of book.
But that kind of feels like
it's leaving me hanging, right?
In yellow, is an
instruction, but how do I
search for Mike in the left
half of the phone book?
Where do I have an
algorithm with which I
can search for someone like Mike Smith?
Well, it's staring us in the face.
I can literally use the exact same
program effectively going up to the top
again and re-running
the same lines of code.
>> So even though this should feel
like a bit of a cyclical definition
where you're answering someone's
question by just sort of asking
the same question again,
like why, why, why?
The reality is because we've hard coded
a couple of special lines, step 4,
which is an if, and step 12, which
is effectively another branch,
because we have those stopgap measures,
this algorithm will terminate if we
find Mike, or if we don't.
But in step 7 and 10 now, we have
what we'll call a recursive algorithm.
And recursion is indeed a powerful idea
that's a little mind bending at first,
that we can now apply as follows.
>> Merge sort will be the last sort that
we look at, at least in class formally.
And it's fundamentally different
from those last three, and certainly
last four if we include bogosort.
Here's the pseudocode for merge sort.
When on input of n elements, so given
an array of size n, if n is less than 2,
return.
So why do I have that
sanity check first?
What's the implication if I hand you
an array whose length n is less than 2?
It's already sorted, obviously, right?
Because the list either has
one element, which is trivially
sorted because it's
the only thing there.
Or, it's of size zero which means
there's nothing to sort, so by nature
it is sorted.
There's just nothing wrong there.
So that's our so-called base case.
>> That is similar in spirit
to what we did with Mike.
If Mike's in the phone book, call him.
If he's not there, give up.
It's a so-called base case, to make sure
this algorithm at the end of the day
will stop in certain circumstances.
>> But here's the leap of faith now, else,
sort the left half of the elements,
then sort the right
half of the elements,
and then merge the sorted halves.
And here's where it feels
like we're copping out.
I've asked you to sort
n elements, and I'm
saying, OK, do it by sorting
the left and sorting the right.
But I am saying one
other thing, and this
is the key theme it seems
in the intuition thus far,
there's this third step of merging.
Which even though it
seems so dumb in spirit,
like just merge things
together, it seems
to be a key step toward the
reassembly of two problems that
were divided ultimately in half.
>> So merge sort, let's do this, if you'll
humor me, with one more demonstration,
just so that we have some
numbers to work with.
Can I exchange eight stress
balls for eight people?
All right, how about you three, you four
in this section, five, six, and let's
do 7, 8, come on up.
OK, yeah OK.
Minus 8, there we go, plus 1.
Excellent.
All right come on up, let's
quickly give you numbers.
Number two, number three, number four,
number five, six, seven, and eight.
I did eight correctly this time.
>> OK, so go ahead if you could, and
let's sort in the original order
that we had yesterday which looked
like this, if you wouldn't mind.
And let's do it in front of the table.
All right, so merge sort.
This is where it's going
to get kind of interesting,
because I seem to be giving myself
so much less information today.
>> So merge sort first of all
on input of n elements,
and is obviously not less than two, it's
eight, so I have some more work to do.
So now mentally we as a class
are now in the else branch,
which means three steps.
First, I have to sort the
left half of the elements.
So how do I go about doing this?
Well, I'm going to kind of
mentally divide the list here,
you don't have to
physically move, and I'm
going to focus only on the
left half of the elements here.
So how do I go about sorting
a list now of size four?
What's my algorithm?
First I check is n less than two, no,
so I proceed to the else block again.
Sort left half of elements.
>> So now again, mentally,
and this is where
you have to accrue a lot of
mental history, if you will.
Now I'm sorting the left
half of the left half.
All right, so now I call my same merge
sorting algorithm, is n less than two?
No, it is two, so I have to sort
the left half, and the right half.
So here we go, sort the left half.
Why don't you just
take one step forward.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Darren.
>> SPEAKER: Dan.
Dan has stepped forward.
>> AUDIENCE: Darren.
SPEAKER: Darren, done.
Did you say Darren or Dan?
>> AUDIENCE: Darren.
>> SPEAKER: Darren.
OK, Darren has stepped
forward and he is now sorted.
And this is almost an
inane claim, right?
I don't really seem to be achieving
anything, but let's proceed.
Now let me sort the right
half of the elements.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Luke.
>> SPEAKER: Luke.
Come on, step forward.
Done, I have sorted Luke.
The left half is now sorted and
the right half is now sorted,
but again, there's a key step here.
What do I next need to do?
Merge the sorted halves.
Now we're going to just have
everyone back and forth in this way,
because I kind of need
some scratch space.
It's almost like these
guys are on a table,
and I need some room
to move them around on.
So I'm going to merge
you guys by looking
at the left half and the right half.
And who obviously comes first,
left half or right half?
So right half, so let's move Luke over
here to Darren's original position.
And now to merge their left half in,
Darren's going to move right there.
>> So feels like almost
a bubble sort effect,
but my fundamental algorithm,
very different this time.
But now's where things get a
little annoying because you
have to rewind mentally
where did I leave off.
I've just merged the sorted halves,
which means I'm where in my algorithm?
I have to sort the right half, right?
>> If you rewind, literally
on the video, you'll
see that we got to this
point of Luke and Darren
by sorting the left
half of the left half.
Then we merged those
sorted halves, which
means the next step is sort the
right half of the left half.
All right, so let's
do this more quickly.
All right, six, I'm going to claim
you are now sorted, come on forward.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Adriano.
>> SPEAKER: Adriano.
Adriano is now sorted.
And what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Alex.
>> SPEAKER: Alex is now sorted.
Left half, right half,
what's the final step?
Merge.
Pretty trivial, so I'm
going to merge in six,
take a step back,
eight, take a step back.
And now notice this is
a useful takeaway, what
is now true about the left half of the
list, irrespective of how we began?
It is sorted.
>> Now it's not sorted in
the big scheme of things,
but it is sorted independently
of the other half.
Now what step am I on if I keep
rewinding how the story began?
Now I have to sort the right half.
So now we're way back at
the beginning of the story,
and let's do this more rapidly.
So I'm going to sort the
right half of the whole list.
What's the next step?
Sort the left half of the right half.
Sort the left half of the
left half of the right half.
And what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Omar.
>> SPEAKER: Omar, step forward, done.
Left half is sorted.
And what's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Chris.
>> SPEAKER: Chris, take a step
forward, you are now sorted.
What's the key step now?
Merge.
So one is going to merge into place
here, if you could take a step back,
and three is going to
take a step back, merge.
So the left half of the
right half, is now sorted.
Frankly, this algorithm feels like we
are wasting way more time than before,
but if we did this in real time, we'll
see what the takeaways going to be.
Now here I am, right
half of the right half,
let me go ahead and sort the left half.
Step forward, what's your name?
AUDIENCE: Ramsey.
SPEAKER: Ramsey is now sorted.
What's your name?
>> AUDIENCE: Marina.
>> SPEAKER: Marina is now sorted as
well, if you take one step forward.
Key step here is now merge, I'm
going to pluck from my two lists,
left and right.
Five is going to come first,
and seven is going to come next.
And again, this is deliberate.
The fact that they're taking
steps forward and back
is meant to represent that we can't
do this algorithm in place as easily
as bubble sort, and selection sort,
and insertion sort where we just
kept swapping people.
I literally need a sort
of scratch paper in which
to put these folks
while I do the merging,
and then I can put them back in place.
And that's key because I'm using a
new resource, space, not just time.
>> OK, this is amazing.
Left half is sorted, right half is
sorted, now that key merging step.
How am I going to merge this?
So if you'll follow my
left hand and right hand,
I'm going to point my left hand
at the left half, my right hand
at the right half, and now I have to
decide step by step whom to merge in.
Who obviously comes first?
Number one.
So come on over here,
here's our scratch pad.
So now number one, and notice
what I'll do with my right hand,
I'm going to move my right hand one
step over to point number three,
and now I have to make
the same decision.
And actually stand right in
front of Luke here if you could,
because this is our scratch pad.
So who comes next?
We have Luke with number two
or Chris with number three.
Obviously Luke, number
two, so you come here.
>> But my left hand now is going to
be incremented to point at Darren,
and here's the key take away with
merging, I'm going to keep doing this,
obviously, if you kind
of follow the logic.
But my hands are never
going to go backwards,
which means I'm only ever moving to
the left with my merging process,
and that's going to be key to
our analysis in just a moment.
>> So now let's finish this up rapidly.
So three comes next,
then four comes next,
and now five comes next, then six,
and seven, and then finally eight.
Feels like the slowest algorithm
yet, but not if we actually
run it at the same sort
of clock speed, so to
speak, with the same
ticking clock as before.
Why?
Well, Let's take a
look at the end result.
>> Let's go back over here, let me
pull up a demonstration visually
of what we just did.
Zooming in here, on this
page here, telling Firefox
that we want to queue
up in this box, let's
say bubble sort, with which
we're now well familiar,
selection sort, which is another
fairly straightforward one,
and now today's merge sort, which
will be our climactic ending.
The reason it took so much longer
here with humans and me verbally is,
obviously, I'm explaining every step.
But if you simply execute this, much
like we did bubble sort and selection
sort not only visually, watch
just how much more efficiently
this leveraging of
division and conquering
can be when applied to a data set that's
not even size eight, but even much,
much bigger.
I give you merge sort, side by
side with these other algorithms.
This is going to get painful
quickly, and the ending
is not particularly climactic,
they just end up sorted.
But the key take away is that
look how much faster merge sort
was, unless you think I'm
just kind of messing with you.
If we do this one final time,
let's reload this, let's go back
and choose bubble sort,
and just for kicks,
let's choose insertion
sort, just for good measure.
And this time again, let's
choose merge sort and let's
actually run these side by side.
>> And it's not, in fact, a fluke.
What I've effectively done is I've
divided my input in half, again,
and again, and again.
And there's only so many times you can
divide your input into halves, left
and right.
What's the formula that we keep seeing
that describes the division in half
again, and again, and again, and again?
>> AUDIENCE: Log n.
>> SPEAKER: Log n.
But then there's one other key step,
this algorithm is not log n steps.
If it were only log n steps,
we would be in the same problem
as before where we can't be
sure everything's sorted.
You have to minimally look at n elements
to be sure n elements are sorted,
otherwise it's a leap of faith.
>> So it's minimally log n steps, but
what about this key merging step
where I merged my left half and right
half and walked across the stage?
How many steps is that to merge?
It's n, but I didn't just
merge the final time.
On each of those nested calls, on each
of those nested merges, I still sorted.
I merged these two guys, then these two
guys, then these two guys and so forth.
>> So I did merging again, and again.
How many times?
So every time I divided the
list in half, I did a merge.
Divide the list in half, do a merge.
So if dividing the list
can be done log n times,
and the merging ultimately takes n
steps, what might be now the upper
bound on the running
time of our algorithm?
n log n.
>> And indeed, that's what
we've achieved here.
So the feel that you see visually when
those three things run side by side
is n squared against n
squared against n log n.
Which fundamentally we'll see,
not only today but in the future,
is much, much faster.
A round of applause for these guys,
I will reward them with stress balls.
Let's adjourn here today, and
we will see you on Monday.